Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame
American Colonial Currency Collection
- South Carolina Currency June 1, 1775South CarolinaJune 1, 1775, SC 06/01/75; ; James Oliphant
  - Fifty Pounds5822 5822, 337; Signers: Alexander Moultrie, Benjamin Waring, John Berwick, (at the side) John Neufville and Peter Bacot.; Size: 101 x 163mm. (front border dimensions 98 x 159; back border dimensions 91 x 138mm)
    All signatures and numbering in brown inks. There are three signatures down the front of the note and three sideways by the seal with the final signature quite faded. This note has a full leafy border design at the indent. On the front is a seal (46mm) depicting a woman seated at the water's edge. She is covered in a wrap to protect her from the rain that is coming down. She watches in the distance as the sun comes out over a town at the other shore. In this context it appears the image was to signify the light after a storm. The image of the sun coming out after a storm or rising over a new nation became a popular theme on revolutionary currency (the MA 1779 emission and the CC $7 note are just a few of the numerous examples). This is a very early use of that imagery, just six weeks after the Battles of Lexington and Concord. One wonders if during the war some holders of this currency may have interpreted the image as Britannia looking over the Atlantic at America? Around the seal is the motto: "POST TENEBRAS LUX" (After darkness there is light) with the date 1775 below. Click here to view a detail of the seal. The engraved back is oriented vertically, with designs and a scroll bearing the motto "For the public good." There are handwritten annotation on the back: Symthe Feloud to GES at Mr. Alegs (?). In the upper left are the initials: J.M., J.C. and E.D. In the lower left are the numbers 34 over 17 5. The paper is watermarked with an animal head.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment. from the EANA mail bid auction of 01/17/98 lot 397.
- South Carolina Currency November 15, 1775South CarolinaNovember 15, 1775, SC 11/15/75; James Oliphant; James Oliphant
  - Five Shillings5754 5754, 338; Signers: Benjamin Waring, Philotheos Cheffelle (or Chiffelle) and George Abbot Hall.; Size: not available.
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. The back is blank.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 4, 1997, lot 314.
  - Thirty Shillings7694 7694, 339; Signers: John Berwick, Benjamin Waring, the third is faded.; Size: not available.
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. The third added signature running vertical to the seal appears to be Alexander Gillon. The back is blank.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 4, 1997, lot 315.
  - Two Pounds, Ten Shillings3403 3403, 340; Signers: William Heirving, Benjamin Waring, Joseph Verree (or Vivree).; Size: 62 x 107mm.
    Numbered and signed in light brown ink. The seal depicts crossed sabers within a crescent moon and the motto PRO LIBERTATE (For Liberty). Completely backed with a stiff paper. The back is blank.
    Acquired through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the Early American History Auction of October 16, 1999, lot 430.
  - Three Pounds, 539
    This is an unnumbered, unsigned remainder. The seal depicts a cannon with the motto, ULTIMA RATIO (The Final Reckoning). Completely backed with newspaper, which includes notices for mare which was found on another's property and the sale of fifty slaves.
    This is an unnumbered and only partially signed remainder. The note is denominated as both eight Spanish milled dollars as as £13 0s0d. The front contains four border cuts and a seal. The 30mm seal depicts a sailing ship with the motto: ". MULTORUM. SPES ." (The hope of many). The reverse contains typeset borders and four Hebrew letters in the corners of the center block as anti counterfeiting devices.
- South Carolina March 6, 1776South CarolinaMarch 6, 1776, SC 03/06/76; ;
  An emission of ฃ750,000 in bills of credit authorized by the Second Provisional Congress of South Carolina. Denominations of ฃ3 and below were typeset with higher denominations printed from engraved copper plates. The notes come in four progressively increasing sizes with the two largest denomination having printed backs. The engraved denominations each have a vignette. Issued on thin white paper with engraved denominations also on blue paper. Denominations issued were: 1s3d, 2s3d, 3s9d, 5s, 6s3d, 12s6d, 17s6d, ฃ1 10s, ฃ1 15s, ฃ2, ฃ2 5s, ฃ3, ฃ15, ฃ25, ฃ50 and ฃ100.
  - Twenty Five Pounds3648 3648, 341; Signers: Jacob Motte, Thomas Savage and Alexander Moultrie.; Size: 81 x 121mm (obverse border design, 79 x 117mm).
    Numbered and signed in light brown inks. The seal (27mm) depicts a falled tree in the foreground with a sturdy tree in full bloom in the background with the motto: "MELIOREM LAPSA LOCAVIT" (Having fallen away it found a better place). To give the roman capital letters in the main text some depth, the tops of the letters were recut slightly higher. This unsuccessful attempt gives the letters the effect of being double struck. Printed on thin white paper. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EAHA mail bid auction of 12/13/97, lot 297, graded Choice About Extremely Fine.
  - Fifty Pounds2101 2101, 342; Signers: Jacob Motte, Samuel Legare, Thomas Savage and William Gibbes.; Size: 86 x 132mm (obverse border design, 85 x 130.5mm; reverse design, 84 x 132mm).
    Numbered and signed in light brown inks with the vertical signature of Gibbes near the left border quite faded. The seal (39mm) depicts military trophies with the motto: ANIMIS OPISBUSQUE PARATI. (Prepared both in spirit and military might). The back contains a geometric design with the motto DEUS PUGNAVIT ET DISSIPANTUR (God has fought and they were dispersed) along the sides in scrolls. There is a handwritten annotation on the back "Wilkenson" (?). Printed on thin blue paper.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EAHA mail bid auction of 03/28/98, lot 374, graded Very Fine.
- South Carolina Currency October 19, 1776South CarolinaOctober 19, 1776, SC 10/19/76; Peter Timothy;
  An emission of ฃ130,000 in bills of credit denominated in Spanish milled dollars but valued in "current" South Carolina pounds. The bills were valued at a rate of one Spanish dollar to 32s6d in South Carolina currency. The face was printed with a engraved plate bearing a vignette and motto while the back of each denomination was typeset. Denominations issued were: $1, $2, $4, $6, $8 and $10. The equivalents in South Carolina pounds as listed on the notes were: $1 (ฃ1 12s6d), $2 (ฃ3 5s), $4 (ฃ6 10s), $6 (ฃ9 15s), $8 (ฃ13) and $10 (ฃ16 5s).
  - Six Dollars1217 1217, 343; Signers: John Sanford Dart, Richard Mercer.; Size: 75 x 93mm (obverse border design, 69.5 x 92mm; reverse border design, 53 x 76mm).
    Numbered in a dark brown ink with both signatures in a light brown ink. The seal depicts wind and waves with the motto: "Turbat sed extollit" (It is turbulant but it elevates). A similar image of a stormy sea is found on seven dollar Continental Currency notes. The imposition of the back is somewhat off center.
    EANA mail bid auction 07/12/97 lot 248. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- South Carolina Currency December 12, 1776Charleston, South CarolinaSouth Carolina23-Dec-76, SC 12/23/76; Peter Timothy;
  An emission of $308,000 (ฃ500,500) in bills of credit entitling the bearer to exchange them for Spanish milled dollars or an equivalent value of gold or silver. Each denomination has a different vignette with a motto taken from the books of J.C. Weigels, Nicholas Verien and Joachim Camerarius. There are wood cut borders on the front giving the value of the note in dollars and pounds. The reverse was typeset using Greek and Hebrew letters as ornaments: they are found near the denomination designation. The notes were printed in 1777 in Charleston by Peter Timothy on a thick brown paper. There were five signers but several partially signed unissued remainders exist as the examples shown below. Denominations issued were: $1 (ฃ1 23s6d), $2 (ฃ3 5s), $3 (ฃ4 17s6d), $4 (ฃ6 10s), $5 (ฃ8 2s6d), $6 (ฃ9 15s), $8 (ฃ13) and $20 (ฃ32 10s).
  - One Dollar, 344; Signer: James Wakefield.; Size: 75 x 111mm (obverse border design, 71 x 108mm; reverse border design, 64 x 100mm).
    This is an unnumbered and only partially signed remainder. The note is denominated as both on Spanish milled dollar as at £1 12s6d. The front contains four border cuts and a seal. The 30mm seal depicts a tree growing through a rock on top of a hill with the motto: ". PER. ARDUA. SURGO ." (I rise up through difficulty). This is a pun on the Latin word arduum which means both a high place and a difficult task. The reverse contains typeset borders and four Hebrew letters in the corners of the center block as anti counterfeiting devices. Also, the letter m in Timothy has been set upside down.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 01/17/98, lot 403.
  - Two Dollars983 983, 345; Signers: James Fisher, William Price, Thomas Jones, Edward Blake.; Size: 74 x 112mm (obverse border design, 71 x 106mm; reverse border design, 60 x 97mm).
    This appears to be a partially signed and numbered remainder. Fully issued notes have five signatures. The note is denominated as both two Spanish milled dollars as at £3 5s. The front contains four border cuts and a seal. The 29mm seal depicts a rooster with the motto: ". ET. SOLI. ET. MARTI. " (For the sun and for Mars). The reverse contains typeset borders and four Hebrew letters in the corners of the center block as anti counterfeiting devices. The obverse of the first issues had the year as 1777, the plate was corrected so later issues, as the one above, bear the correct year.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Chicago Paper Money Auction of 2/17/2000, lot 1034, graded as extremely fine.
  - Three Dollars1099 1099, 346; Signer: James Wakefield.; Size: 70 x 107mm (obverse border design, 69 x 107mm; reverse border design, 59 x 96mm).
    This is a partially signed remainder, the numbering appears to have been added at a later date. The note is denominated as both one Spanish milled dollar as £4 17s6d. The front contains four border cuts and a seal. The 29mm seal depicts what appears to be a tree stump. Newman calls this an oracle without explanation. The motto reads: ": FATA. VIAM. INVENIENT ." (The fates will find a way). The reverse contains typeset borders and four Hebrew letters in the corners of the center block as anti-counterfeiting devices.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/02/95, lot 532.
  - Four Dollars339 339, 347; Signers: George Cooke, William Greenwood, Thomas Jones, Edward Blake (faded written sideways).; Size: 73 x 112mm (obverse border design, 70 x 108mm; reverse border design, 60 x 97mm).
    This appears to be a partially signed and numbered remainder. Fully issued notes have five signatures. The note is denominated as both four Spanish milled dollars as at £6 10s. The front contains four border cuts and a seal. The 29mm seal depicts a boat at sea named the Actaeon that is on fire with the motto: ". THE ACTAEON.. IRAM. PRUDENTIA. VINCIT. " (The Actaeon. Prudence conquers anger). The reverse contains typeset borders and four Hebrew letters in the corners of the center block as anti-counterfeiting devices. In the bottom margin of the reverse is the handwritten annotation "I John [last name obsucured by a stain]." The obverse of the first issues had the year as 1777, the plate was corrected so later issues, as the one above, bear the correct year.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Chicago Paper Money Auction of 2/17/2000, lot 1035, graded as very fine.
  - Eight Dollars, 348; Signer: James Wakefield.; Size: 75 x 114mm (obverse border design, 72 x 111mm; reverse border design, 67 x 108mm).
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 593. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Twenty Dollars1807 1807, 349; Signers: George Cooke, Nathaniel Russell, William Greenwood.; Size: 72 x 116mm (obverse border design, 69 x 114mm; reverse border design, 68 x 116mm).
    This appears to be a partially signed and numbered remainder. Fully issued notes have five signatures. The numbering is quite faded. The note is denominated as both twenty Spanish milled dollars as at £32 10s0d. The front contains four border cuts with cornucopias at the top and a seal. The 29mm seal depicts a bull with the motto: ". AUT. MORS. AUT. VICTORIA. " (Either death or victory). The reverse contains typeset borders and four Hebrew letters in the corners of the center block as anti-counterfeiting devices. Note the top border contains a skull with cross bones flanked by an hourglass on either side followed by a design and then a harp.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 5/23/98, lot 455, graded as choice extremely fine.
  - Six Dollars, 538; Signer: James Wakefield
    This is an unnumbered and only partially signed remainder. The note is denominated as both six Spanish milled dollars as as £9 15s0d. The front contains four border cuts and a seal. The 30mm seal depicts a camel with the motto: "NEC ONUS NEC META GRAVABIT ." (Neither burden nor danger will force me down). The reverse contains typeset borders and four Hebrew letters in the corners of the center block as anti counterfeiting devices.
- South Carolina Currency February 14, 1777South CarolinaFebruary 14, 1777, SC 02/14/77; ;
  An emission of $308,000 (ฃ500,500) in bills of credit entitling the bearer to current money. The engraved obverse of both denominations have a different vignette with a motto. The reverse is typeset. There are three to four signatures on each bill. Printed on brown paper. Denominations issued were: $20 (ฃ32 10s) and $30 (ฃ48 15s).
  - Twenty Dollars5871 5871, 350; Signers: William Logan, Samuel Legar, Robert William Powell, Edward Blake.; Size: 78 x 111mm (obverse border design, 74 x 109mm; reverse border design, 68 x 105mm).
    Seal depicts a bird flying out of an opened cage; motto above reads: "Ubi libertas ibi patria" (Where there is liberty, there is the homeland). On the back in the top right cornet is a pencil annotation: "W.V. 12 Dec 77."
    EANA mail bid auction 5/20/96 lot 595. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Thirty Dollars462 462, 351; Signers: William Logan, Samuel Legar, Robert William Powell.; Size: 75 x 110mm (obverse border design, 74 x 109mm; reverse border design, 68 x 104mm).
    Seal depicts a traveler with a backpack; motto above reads: "Misera servitus omnis" (All slavery is wretched).
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 478. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- South Carolina Currency April 10, 1778South CarolinaApril 10, 1778, SC 04/10/78; ;
  An emission of ฃ100,000 in legal tender lawful money. The obverse of these smaller sized bills is engraved with a different vignette on each denomination. The backs are blank. According to Newman the 20s plate still exists. The legal tender status of this and all earlier issues was revoked in the act of February 6, 1782. There are two signers on each note. Denominations issued were: 2s6d, 3s9d, 5s, 7s6d, 10s, 15s, 20s and 30s.
  - Two Shillings, Six Pence8603 8603, 352; Signers: William Mathews, Henry Crouch.; Size: 65 x 134mm. (obverse border design 57 x 93mm).
    Seal depicts two cornucopiae. Reverse blank. Large selvege at the left border and a small selvege at the top border. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the the Robert H. Gore Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Chicago Paper Money Exposition Auction no. 196 of February 17, 2000, lot 1038.
  - Three Shillings, Nine Pence9473 9473, 353; Signers: John Neufville, Jr., Henry Crouch.; Size: 62 x 99mm. (obverse border design 57 x 92mm).
    Seal depicts a beaver on a river bank with a stick in its mouth. Reverse blank. Paper watermarked "Zoon.. .?" The unprinted back has a modern annotation 1702 along the right edge.
    From the Robert H. Gore Numismatic Collection.
  - Five Shillings863 863, 354; Signers: John Beale, John Peronneau.; Size: 63 x 106mm. (obverse border design 56 x 93mm).
    The seal in the lower right corner depicts a phoenix rising from the flames. The phoenix is a mythological bird resembling the eagle but with red and gold feathers. According to classical legend every 500 years the phoenix made a nest and then died. The new phoenix carried the parent's body to the temple of the sun god where it was consumed on a funeral pyre. During the Middle Ages this story was conflated so that it was thought a new phoenix would arise from the flaming ashes of parent's funeral pyre. This note is signed and numbered in light brown ink. The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96 lot 729. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Ten Shillings672 672, 355; Signers: John Beale, John Peronneau.; Size: 62 x 100mm. (obverse border design 56 x 94mm).
    Seal depicts a palmetto tree on a river bank with a fort (probably Charleston) on the opposite bank. The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 600. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Fifteen Shillings, 356; Signers: Jacob Read.; Size: 62 x 101mm. (obverse border design 56 x 93mm).
    Seal depicts the sun rising over a river bank. The reverse has a sketch of a face looking to the left in pencil and a second sketch of the lower half of a face (nose to the neck) looking to the right in crayon on the side. To view the crayon drawing properly oriented click here.
    Purchased through the the Robert H. Gore Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Chicago Paper Money Exposition Auction no. 196 of February 17, 2000, lot 1042.
  - Thirty Shillings10378 10378, 357; Signers: Nicholas Langford, William Roper.; Size: 62 x 96mm. (obverse border design 56 x 93mm).
    Seal depicts a personification of Hope holding a branch in her left hand and with her right hand resting on an anchor. The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/26/97 lot 329. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Twenty Shillings4763 4763, 540; Signers: John Neufville, Charles Pinckney, Jr.
    Seal depicts a horse running from right to left. The back is blank.
- South Carolina Currency February 8, 1776Charleston, South CarolinaSouth CarolinaFebruary 8, 1779, SC 02/08/79; ; Thomas Coram
  An emission of $1,000,000 in bills of credit in legal tender lawful money. The bills were sumptuously engraved by Thomas Coram in Charleston. Coram signed the $50, $70 and $90 notes (unfortunately the signature has been cut off the $50 and $90 examples below but is on the $70 example). There are different vignettes and mottos on the front of each denomination while the reverse has an elaborate scene, some from classical antiquity. The legal tender status of this and all earlier issues was revoked in the act of February 6, 1782. Denominated in dollars (Spanish milled dollars) as well as in South Carolina pounds. Denominations issued were: $40 (ฃ65), $50 (ฃ81 5s), $60 (ฃ97 10s), $70 (ฃ113 15s), $80 (ฃ130), $90 (ฃ146 5s) and $100 (ฃ162 10s).
  - Fifty Dollars1265 1265, 359; Signers: John Hopton, George Cooke, John Smyth.; Size: 70 x 118mm (obverse border design, 70 x 118mm).
    The front of the bill depicts Providence pointing to a globe of the earth; the motto reads: "PROVIDENTIA NOSTRIS PRAESIDEAT" (Let foresight guide our people). The back depicts Atlas holding a boulder. The front of the bill is perfectly centered, but the imposition of the reverse on our example is off center: there is a large margin at the top but the signature of Coram and the pound equivalency have been cut off at the bottom.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr, Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/2/95, lot 536.
  - Sixty Dollars3962 3962, 360; Signers: Charles Atkins, John Smyth, John Scott.; Size: 71 x 120mm (obverse border design, 70 x 120mm).
    The front of the bill contains a seated classical figure (possibly Cerces) with a cornucopia. The motto reads: "MUTUA DEFENSIO TUTISSIMAM" (Mutual defense is safest). On the back is a collage with a lyre, two crossed brass horns and two crossed flags.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr, Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/2/95, lot 537.
  - Seventy Dollars9243 9243, 361; Signers: Charles Atkins, George Cooke, John Scott.; Size: 72 x 121mm (obverse border design, 71 x 121mm; reverse design 65 x 108mm).
    The front of the bill contains a personification of Hope leaning against an anchor; the motto reads: "SPES MENTIS SOLATIO ." (Hope is the solace of the mind). The back shows the bound Prometheus attacked by a vulture and is signed by the engraver Thomas Coram. For a detail of the T. Coram signature click here. There is a modern annotation in black ink in the upper left corner "XX.332.71" and a rust stain from a paper clip at the area of the engraved signature.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr, Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 1/17/98, lot 412. Previously this item was lot 550 in the Altman-Haffner Sale conducted by the Pine Tree Auction Company, April 29-30, 1975 in New York City
  - Eighty Dollars2047 2047, 362; Signers: James Bentham, Sims White, Philip Prioleau.; Size: 73 x 120mm (obverse border design, 72 x 120mm; reverse border design 63 x 115mm).
    The front of the bill depicts a man in classical dress holding a sword over a flaming altar; the motto reads: "Constantia durissima vincit" (The firmest constancy will conquer). On the back is a collage with a shield, a liberty cap, brass horns, arrows, palm leaves and olive branches. Also on the back are notations in pen: "1389: n...6" and a partly cut off sum of numbers: 13- + 9- = 22- (the 77 or 79 is added) with 299 at the bottom.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr, Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/2/95, lot 538.
  - Ninety Dollars7018 7018, 363; Signers: George Cooke, Charles Atkins, John Smyth.; Size: 73 x 120mm (obverse border design, 71 x 119mm; reverse border design horizontal: 116mm, vertical dimensions trimmed in this example).
    The front of the bill depicts a warrior in classical armor holding a spear. The motto reads "Armis concurrite campo." (With arms we run together into the field of battle). The reverse is off center, so that the top has been cropped. On the back is Hercules wrestling the Nemean Lion. In the scroll below the D in DOLLARS in small letters is "No. II". Although Newman states the reverse of this denomination is signed, the signature appears to be cropped off this example.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr, Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 11/16/96, lot 735.
- South Carolina Currency July 6, 1789South CarolinaJuly 6, 1789, SC 07/06/89; ; Abernethie